Again, you're going to have to read and tell me which you think is human. Poem 1: Red flags the reason for pretty flags. / And ribbons. Ribbons of flags / And wearing material / Reasons for wearing material. (...) Poem 2: A wounded deer leaps highest, / I've heard the daffodil I've heard the flag to-day / I've heard the hunter tell; / 'Tis but the ecstasy of death, / And then the brake is almost done (...) OK, time is up. So hands up if you think Poem 1 was written by a human. Hands up if you think Poem 2 was written by a human. Whoa, that's a lot more people. So you'd be surprised to find that Poem 1 was written by the very human poet Gertrude Stein. And Poem 2 was generated by an algorithm called RKCP. Now before we go on, let me describe very quickly and simply, how RKCP works. So RKCP is an algorithm designed by Ray Kurzweil, who's a director of engineering at Google and a firm believer in artificial intelligence. So, you give RKCP a source text, it analyzes the source text in order to find out how it uses language, and then it regenerates language that emulates that first text. So in the poem we just saw before, Poem 2, the one that you all thought was human, it was fed a bunch of poems by a poet called Emily Dickinson it looked at the way she used language, learned the model, and then it regenerated a model according to that same structure. But the important thing to know about RKCP is that it doesn't know the meaning of the words it's using. The language is just raw material, it could be Chinese, it could be in Swedish, it could be the collected language from your Facebook feed for one day. It's just raw material. And nevertheless, it's able to create a poem that seems more human than Gertrude Stein's poem, and Gertrude Stein is a human. So what we've done here is, more or less, a reverse Turing test. So Gertrude Stein, who's a human, is able to write a poem that fools a majority of human judges into thinking that it was written by a computer. Therefore, according to the logic of the reverse Turing test, Gertrude Stein is a computer. (Laughter) Feeling confused? I think that's fair enough. So far we've had humans that write like humans, we have computers that write like computers, we have computers that write like humans, but we also have, perhaps most confusingly, humans that write like computers. So what do we take from all of this? Do we take that William Blake is somehow more of a human than Gertrude Stein? Or that Gertrude Stein is more of a computer than William Blake? (Laughter) These are questions I've been asking myself for around two years now, and I don't have any answers. But what I do have are a bunch of insights about our relationship with technology. So my first insight is that, for some reason, we associate poetry with being human. So that when we ask, "Can a computer write poetry?" we're also asking, "What does it mean to be human and how do we put boundaries around this category? How do we say who or what can be part of this category?" This is an essentially philosophical question, I believe, and it can't be answered with a yes or no test, like the Turing test. I also believe that Alan Turing understood this, and that when he devised his test back in 1950, he was doing it as a philosophical provocation. So my second insight is that, when we take the Turing test for poetry, we're not really testing the capacity of the computers because poetry-generating algorithms, they're pretty simple and have existed, more or less, since the 1950s. What we are doing with the Turing test for poetry, rather, is collecting opinions about what constitutes humanness. So, what I've figured out, we've seen this when earlier today, we say that William Blake is more of a human than Gertrude Stein. Of course, this doesn't mean that William Blake was actually more human or that Gertrude Stein was more of a computer. It simply means that the category of the human is unstable. This has led me to understand that the human is not a cold, hard fact. Rather, it is something that's constructed with our opinions and something that changes over time. So my final insight is that the computer, more or less, works like a mirror that reflects any idea of a human that we show it. We show it Emily Dickinson, it gives Emily Dickinson back to us. We show it William Blake, that's what it reflects back to us. We show it Gertrude Stein, what we get back is Gertrude Stein. More than any other bit of technology, the computer is a mirror that reflects any idea of the human we teach it. So I'm sure a lot of you have been hearing a lot about artificial intelligence recently. And much of the conversation is, can we build it? Can we build an intelligent computer? Can we build a creative computer? What we seem to be asking over and over is can we build a human-like computer? But what we've seen just now is that the human is not a scientific fact, that it's an ever-shifting, concatenating idea and one that changes over time. So that when we begin to grapple with the ideas of artificial intelligence in the future, we shouldn't only be asking ourselves, "Can we build it?" But we should also be asking ourselves, "What idea of the human do we want to have reflected back to us?" This is an essentially philosophical idea, and it's one that can't be answered with software alone, but I think requires a moment of species-wide, existential reflection. Thank you. (Applause)
De nuevo, tendrán que leer y decirme qué poema piensan que fue escrito por un humano. Poema 1: Banderas rojas, la razón de hermosas banderas. / Y el blasón. Blasones de banderas / Y materiales. / Razones para lucir materiales. (...) Poema 2: Un ciervo herido salta más alto, / He oído al narciso. / He oído la bandera hoy / He oído al cazador decir; / No es más que el éxtasis de la muerte / Y luego es casi irrefrenable. (...) Muy bien, tiempo. Levanten la mano si piensan que el Poema 1 fue escrito por un humano. Levanten la mano si piensan que el Poema 2 fue escrito por un humano. Guau, son muchos más. Les sorprenderá saber que el Poema 1 fue escrito por la mismísima Gertrude Stein. Y el Poema 2 fue generado por un algoritmo llamado RKCP. Pero antes de continuar describiré, simple y rápidamente, cómo funciona RKCP. El RKCP es un algoritmo diseñado por Ray Kurzweil, un director de ingeniería de Google que cree firmemente en la inteligencia artificial. Se le proporciona a RKCP un texto fuente, El RKCP analiza el texto para detectar cómo se usa el lenguaje, y luego vuelve a generar el lenguaje que emula al primer texto. El poema que vimos antes, el Poema 2, el que todos pensaron que era humano, fue creado a base de muchos poemas escritos por la poetisa Emily Dickinson; analizó la forma en que ella usaba el lenguaje, aprendió el modelo, y luego volvió a generar un modelo siguiendo la misma estructura. Pero lo importante a saber de RKCP es que no conoce el significado de las palabras que usa. El lenguaje es solo materia prima, podría ser chino, podría ser sueco, podría ser todo lo escrito en su muro de Facebook a lo largo del día. Un idioma no es más que materia prima para la machina. Y, no obstante, es capaz de crear un poema que parece más humano que el poema de Gertrude Stein, y Gertrude Stein es un ser humano. Aquí hemos hecho, más o menos, una prueba de Turing inversa. Gertrude Stein, humana, puede escribir un poema que lleva a pensar a la mayoría de los jueces humanos que fue escrito por una máquina. Por lo tanto, según la lógica de la prueba de Turing inversa, Gertrude Stein es una máquina. (Risas) ¿Están confundidos? Pienso que es normal. Hasta ahora tuvimos humanos que escribían como humanos, tenemos máquinas que escriben como máquinas, tenemos máquinas que escriben como humanos, pero también tenemos, quizá lo que más confunde, humanos que escriben como máquinas. ¿Qué aprendemos de todo esto? ¿Que William Blake en cierta forma es más humano que Gertrude Stein? ¿O que Gertrude Stein es más autómata que William Blake? (Risas) Son preguntas que me he hago desde hace dos años y no tengo respuestas. Pero tengo un montón de ideas sobre nuestra relación con la tecnología. Mi primera idea es que, por alguna razón, asociamos la poesía con el ser humano. Por eso cuando nos preguntamos: "¿Puede una máquina escribir poesía?" también preguntamos: "¿Qué significa ser humanos y cómo circunscribimos esta categoría? ¿Cómo decidimos quién o qué puede pertenecer a esta categoría?" Creo que es esencialmente una cuestión filosófica, que no podemos solucionar con una prueba binaria, como la prueba de Turing. Creo que Alan Turing también entendió esto, y que cuando ideó su prueba allá por los años 50, lo pensó como una provocación filosófica. Mi segunda idea es que, si aplicamos la prueba de Turing a la poesía, en realidad no probamos la capacidad de las máquinas porque los algoritmos generadores de poesía son bastante simples y han existido, más o menos, desde los años 50. En cambio, lo que hacemos con la prueba de Turing en la poesía es recolectar opiniones sobre el significado de lo humano. Yo descubrí que, lo hemos visto hoy más temprano, decíamos que William Blake es más humano que Gertrude Stein. Claro, esto no significa que William Blake sea en realidad más humano ni que Gertrude Stein sea más autómata. Significa simplemente que la categoría de lo humano es inestable. Esto me ha llevado a comprender que lo humano no es un hecho rígido, frío. Más bien, es algo construido con opiniones y algo que cambia con el tiempo. Y mi última idea es que la máquina funciona más o menos como un espejo que refleja cualquier idea humana que le mostramos. Le mostramos a Emily Dickinson y nos devuelve Emily Dickinson. Le mostramos a William Blake y eso es lo que emula. Le mostramos a Gertrude Stein y crea en base al estilo de Gertrude Stein. Más que cualquier otra tecnología, la máquina es un espejo que refleja una idea del humano que le mostramos. Estoy seguro de que muchos de Uds. habrán oído mucho recientemente sobre la inteligencia artificial. Y el centro de la conversación es si podemos crearla. ¿Podemos crear una máquina inteligente? ¿Podemos crear una máquina creativa? Parece que nos preguntamos sin cesar: ¿Podemos crear una máquina semejante a un humano? Pero hasta ahora hemos visto que lo humano no es un hecho científico, sino una idea armoniosa y siempre cambiante que cambia con el tiempo. Cuando empecemos a debatir las ideas de una inteligencia artificial en el futuro, no solo deberíamos preguntarnos: "¿Podemos construirla?" También deberíamos preguntarnos: "¿Qué idea de lo humano desearíamos ver reflejada en nosotros?" Esta es una idea esencialmente filosófica que no puede responderse solo con software, sino que requiere un momento de reflexión existencial de la especie. Gracias. (Aplausos)